Everyone must have heard of high blood pressure, right?
大家應該都有聽過高血壓吧?
Raise your hand
沒有聽過的舉手
There must be a thick myocardial infarction.
應該都有厚那心肌梗塞呢
Yes, have you heard of CPR and AED?
有吧，CPR跟AED也有聽過吧
both
都有喔
I just had some small problems, sorry
剛剛有一些些小問題不好意思
Then wait, I hope there will be some
然後等下我希望會有一些些的互動希望大家可以給我一些的Feedback
I'll say it's important, it's important
我等下會說很重要很重要
This is very important, wait for the test and you will pass the test.
這個很重要就是等一下考試一定會考的
There will be 3 questions in my part, you should remember
我的部分會有3題大家要記得
Everyone knows high blood pressure, so do
大家都知道高血壓那大家知道我們的血壓是怎麼量測出來的嗎
How is blood pressure measured
血壓是怎麼量測出來的
sphygmomanometer
血壓計
How does the blood pressure monitor measure?
血壓計怎麼量的呢
I don't know, I will broadcast a short video later, you can watch it
不知道好我等一下會播一個小短片，大家可以看一下
How is blood pressure measured
血壓是怎麼量的
Did we just see a heart beating there
我們剛剛是不是有看到一顆心臟在那裡跳動
Well, our heart is like a pump
那其實我們的心臟就像是一顆幫浦
He'll help us pump the blood that goes back to the heart like this
他會幫我們把血液流回到心臟的那些血用幫浦這樣子打出去
Blood pressure is the pressure in the blood
血壓就是血液中的壓力它在血管壁中的壓力
It's called our blood pressure
量出來的就叫做我們的血壓
Let's wait a minute. The first blood pressure
我們等一下第一個量出來的血壓叫做收縮壓
Now this is the systolic blood pressure, and
現在這個就是收縮壓那等一下還會看到我們的舒張壓
Okay, so everyone should know how to measure blood pressure.
好那這樣子血壓是怎麼量測出來的大家應該比較清楚了吧
Then let's take a look
那我們再來看一下
Do you know what our normal blood pressure is?
大家知道我們血壓正常值是多少嗎?
Our normal blood pressure is 80 low from 120
我們血壓正常值是在120低的80
this is very important
這個很重要很重要
Very important
很重要
Ordinary people may think that if my blood pressure
平常人啊他可能會覺得如果我的血壓大於120小於130這樣O不OK
Yes, but the problem is that this is the pre-hypertension
可以但是問題是這個就是我們高血壓的前期
What maintenance we can usually do I'll tell you later
我們平常可以做什麼保養我等一下會跟大家說
Then if your blood pressure is already high enough
那如果說血壓你已經高到他所說的高血壓危機
What should you do if your systolic blood pressure is greater
收縮壓大於180舒張壓大於120的話你要怎麼辦
What are your symptoms if your blood pressure is too high?
如果你們血壓過高你們會有什麼症狀
Some people may experience headaches
有可能有些人會有頭痛的情形
right
對不對
Some people with high blood pressure should have headaches,
有人血壓高應該都會有頭痛 或者說高到一個不行可能就會有頭暈的情形
Then I want to ask
那我想問一下
How often do you have your blood pressure measured?
大家你們的血壓都多久量測一次
We ordinary people will feel that there is no physical
我們平常人都會覺得沒有身體不舒服為什麼要量血壓
In fact, the government's recommendation is to
其實政府建議就是說我們一般人的正常血壓
In fact, normal people need to measure their
正常人其實每半年到一年就要量測一次血壓
Every six months to one year
每半年到一年
Well that means if your family has no history of genetic diseases
好那就是如果說你們家沒有什麼遺傳疾病史
Then I measure my blood pressure and it's pretty normal.
然後自己平常量測血壓也都蠻正常的
It doesn't matter if you measure your blood pressure during the health check
那健檢的時候量測血壓沒有關係
But the question is if
但是問題來了如果說
you have diabetes today
今天你有糖尿病
kidney disease
腎臟病
So how often do we measure
那我們要多久量一次
The government's recommendation is that twice a month is enough.
政府的建議是說每個月兩次也就可以了
If you usually measure blood pressure and do not have high blood pressure
如果你平時量測血壓沒有血壓高的狀況
Monitor your blood pressure every month
每個月要去監測一下自己的血壓
But if so today you are a patient with high blood pressure
但是如果說所以今天你是高血壓的病患
Blood pressure is too high
本身血壓就偏高了
what to do
那要怎麼辦
how often do we measure
我們要多久量一次
Tomorrow is morning and night
明天的話就是早上跟晚上
Measure blood pressure during these two periods
這兩個時段去量測血壓
Why choose morning and night?
為什麼會選擇早上跟晚上呢？
In the morning, just woke up, blood pressure fluctuated
早上的話剛睡醒來血壓起伏
The float comparison won't be so big
浮動比較不會這麼的大
Do we also sort out our emotions before going to bed at night?
晚上要睡覺之前我們是不是也會整理一下我們情緒心情
At that time, our blood pressure measurement fluctuations were not so large.
那時候我們的血壓量測浮動比較不會這麼的大
Blood pressure will be more accurate
量出來的血壓就會比較準確一些
How often do you think 80-year-olds should be measured?
80歲的老年人呢你們覺得要多久量測一次
if he said
他如果說
No history of hypertension
沒有高血壓疾病史
It is normal to measure blood pressure normally,
平常量測血壓也都蠻正常的也是建議每個月量測一次就可以了
But if you find that his blood pressure is measured, it seems to fluctuate every time
但是如果說你有發現到他的血壓 量測起伏好像每次量都
If it is not so stable, I will measure the movement every day
不是這麼穩定的話我就要每天量測的動作
Have you noticed the elderly over the age of 80?
大家有沒有注意到80歲以上的長者
Why is his systolic blood pressure lower than 150?
他的血壓為什麼收縮壓是要低於150
Have you ever thought about
大家有沒有想過
Because the elasticity of the blood vessels in the elderly is relatively poor
因為老年人他的血管彈性比較不好
So the doctor would suggest that it doesn't
所以醫生會比較建議說沒關係你血壓低於150就好了
There are two types of high blood pressure
那我們的高血壓類型有分兩種
The first is primary
第一種是原發性
If it is primary, it may be because of the family history.
原發性的話呢他有可能因為家族有遺傳史
Or older
或者是年紀比較大了
Or you are smoking
或者是本身有在抽煙
or it could be
或者是
I believe the person with high blood pressure is in the workplace
我相信有高血壓的人他在工作場上
The blood pressure measurement data will be more than
量測血壓的數據一定會比
Blood pressure usually measured at home is still high
平常在家裡量測的血壓還高
right
對不對
don't know it's okay
不知道沒關係
Next time if you say take your blood pressure at home
下次你如果說在家裡量血壓
you can remember your numbers
你可以記得你數字
And then when I say that after the meeting with the boss, I get emotional
然後當如果說跟老闆開完會之後情緒一來
Then stress
然後壓力一緊張
I'm sure your blood pressure will be higher then
我相信那時候你們的血壓一定都會量得比較高
You can try it next time
大家下次可以來試試看
After talking about primary, there is another called secondary
講到原發性他之後還有一個叫做續發性
It may be caused by factors of your disease
他有可能會是因為你的疾病的因素導致的
for example
例如說
diabetes thyroid
糖尿病甲狀腺
There are some chronic diseases that can affect the function of our blood vessels
有一些慢性疾病他都會影響到我們血管的功能
The condition that indirectly affects our blood pressure
間接的影響到我們血壓的狀況
So let's hear what the doctor has to say
那我們來聽聽一下醫生他是怎麼說的
I want to ask everyone
我想問一下大家
red neck is high blood pressure
脖子紅紅是不是高血壓
Not necessarily, so how do you know
不一定嘛 那這樣子你要怎麼知道
Your neck is red, will you take your blood pressure?
脖子紅紅你們會不會去量一下血壓
Won't
不會
Okay, let's see what the doctor has to say
好那我們再看一下醫生怎麼說
The doctor just said that high blood
醫生剛才有說高血壓會引起很多身體器官造成傷害
Do you know what the damage is?
大家知道有哪些傷害嗎?
High blood pressure can affect many organs if say
高血壓它會影響到很多器官如果說
High blood pressure affects our brain
血壓高它影響到我們的腦部
what will happen
會有什麼狀況
stroke
中風
have points
有分
Our strokes are divided into hemorrhagic and obstructive strokes
我們中風有分出血性跟阻塞性的中風
What are the symptoms of stroke, big brother, can you share?
中風的症狀有哪些大哥你可以分享一下嗎
Everyone should have seen a stroke
大家應該都有看過中風的狀況
Some mild strokes and some serious strokes
有些有分輕微的腦中風有些分嚴重性的腦中風
some mild stroke he may
有些輕微的腦中風他可能
After training, he may still be able to walk like a normal person
發病之後再做訓練 他可能還可以像一般人一樣做行走的動作
But you can see that his gait will be less like us normal people.
可是你可以看到他在走路的步態就會比較不像我們正常人
It will feel a little biased, if it is serious
會有點一偏一偏的感覺那如果說嚴重的話
Maybe it's all in the hospital bed
可能就是整個都躺在病床上
The part that needs help
需要人家來協助的部分
If this high blood pressure affects our eyes
如果說這個血壓高它影響到我們的眼睛的話
What do you think about our eyes?
大家覺得我們的眼睛會怎麼樣
If high blood pressure affects our eyes
血壓高他如果說影響到我們的眼睛
Our eyes have many tiny blood vessels
我們眼睛其實有很多的細小血管
Pressure vessels burst
壓力大血管就會爆裂
May cause temporary blindness
有可能會導致暫時性的失明
Do you feel scared if you can't see it?
大家如果看不到會不會覺得很害怕
It should be more frightening than the feeling of not being able to hear it.
應該會比那種聽不到的感覺更害怕吧
Yes, so we need to take good care of our eyes
對所以我們的眼睛也要好好的保護一下
What if high blood pressure affects our blood vessels?
那如果說血壓高影響到我們的血管
what might we be
我們有可能會怎樣
may affect our aorta
有可能會影響到我們的主動脈
there may be
可能會有
A tumor or aortic valve dissection may be the case here
一個腫瘤或者是主動脈瓣剝離的情形這裡都說不定
if blood pressure
如果說血壓
it affects our kidneys
它影響到我們的腎臟
what if it's serious
嚴重的話會怎樣
In severe cases, kidney dialysis may be
嚴重的話可能會到洗腎
You see this high blood pressure is really bad, he's a badass
你看這個高血壓真的是很糟糕 他是一個壞蛋
What if he affects our hearts?
那如果說他影響到我們的心臟呢
myocardial infarction angina pectoris
心肌梗塞心絞痛對不對
That's the scariest thing
那這個也是一個最可怕的事情
Yesterday or the day before yesterday, everyone should have seen the news, right?
昨天還是前天大家應該都有看到新聞吧
The one in Pingtung
屏東的那一個
Okay, I'll play the video later
好我等一下放一下影片
In fact, these are the symptoms of high blood pressure
那其實高血壓的症狀有這些
Do you have any tinnitus, numbness in hands and feet,
大家有嗎有沒有常常耳鳴手腳麻木心悸吃不下想吐
I think should not be
應該沒有吧
Everyone is in good shape
大家的身體都保持得很好不錯不錯
What if our high blood pressure
那如果說我們的高血壓
usually
平時
If you have high blood pressure, you have seen a doctor
血壓高的話你有去看醫生醫生有開藥給你們吃
Most likely these drugs
最主要可能會有這些藥物
The first is a calcium blocker
第一種是鈣離子阻斷器
What about his words?
那他的話呢
Everyone should be taking antihypertensive drugs
大家應該如果是有在吃降壓藥
Or his family members are taking antihypertensive drugs
或者是家人他有在吃降壓藥
The most common is probably this one called Norvasc
最常見的可能就是這個叫Norvasc
Its side effects may be noticed
它的副作用可能大家要注意一下
Be careful when you eat
平時要吃東西的話也要注意一下
Our Mid-Autumn Festival is coming soon
我們中秋節快要到了
we will eat grapefruit
我們會吃柚子
Whether it's a pomelo or a grapefruit, it has flavonoids in it.
不管是璠柚葡萄柚他裡面都有類黃酮
It affects the metabolism of our liver
它會影響到我們肝臟的代謝
He wants a drug, almost all of our drugs are metabolized in the liver, you know?
他這個要藥物我們的藥物幾乎都會在肝臟代謝大家知道嗎
Then if we eat something containing flavonoids
那如果說我們吃了有含類黃酮的東西影響我們肝臟的代謝
So these drugs like this Norvasc
那這些藥物比如說這個Norvasc
he will
他就會
The effect of this medicine will be in our body
這個藥效就會在我們身體裡面
continued
一直持續
But we take this medicine every day
但是我們這個藥又是每天要吃的
That medicine has been in our body forever
那藥效一直在我們身體裡面一直持續
It may cause our body to have low blood pressure
它有可能導致我們的身體會有低血壓的情形
Low blood pressure can make us dizzy
低血壓可能就會導致我們頭暈
You may faint in the end
暈到最後可能就會暈倒
Or the whole body is uncomfortable
或者是說整個身體都不舒服的情形
The second one
再來第二種
Inhibit vasoconstriction
抑制血管收縮
Here he wrote
他這裡有寫到
He wrote here that we should be cautious about eating potassium-containing diets
他這裡有寫到我們平時要謹慎攝取含鉀鹽的飲食
Anyone know why he's advising us to be careful about potassium salts?
大家知道為什麼他要建議我們要謹慎攝取含鉀鹽嗎
because of these drugs
因為這些藥物呢
this drug
這一種藥物
His side effects can make our blood oxygen rise
他的副作用會讓我們的血氧升高
what we usually eat
平常我們在吃的
Do you know what foods contain potassium?
食物裡面有含鉀的大家知道有哪些嗎
What?
有哪些?
banana
香蕉
kiwi
奇異果
So take these medicines
所以再吃這些藥物的
You may need to pay attention to your diet
你可能平時在飲食方面就要注意一下
There's also a diuretic
那還有一個利尿劑
Usually the most common is Spiratone
平常最常見就是Spiratone
Diuretics are known as diuretics
利尿劑的話大家就會知道是利尿利尿
Diuresis is to help us urinate
利尿的話就是幫助我們排尿
Let our body excrete more water
讓我們身體裡面的水份多排出來一些
If so, would we suggest that he take this medicine at night?
那他的話我們會不建議他晚上吃這個藥
Because we probably don't want to get up at night to go to the toilet all the time.
因為我們應該都不希望自己晚上一直爬起來上廁所吧
Therefore, doctors recommend taking this medicine during the day.
所以這一種藥醫生都會建議在白天的時候服用
This will not affect your sleep at night
這樣才不會影響到晚上的睡眠
The last one is the alpha blocker
最後一種就是甲型阻斷劑
He actually acts on our blood vessels to dilate
他其實作用在我們的血管擴張
So if you dilate this blood vessel, when we change positions quickly
所以如果說你擴張了這個血管那我們在快速轉換姿勢的時候
makes us feel dizzy
會導致我們頭暈不舒服
This is called postural hypotension
這個就叫做姿勢性的低血壓
So sometimes we have to pay attention when taking this drug again.
所以再吃這種藥物的時候有時候我們就要注意一下
We can't get up after a quick squat
我們不能快速蹲下後站起來
Because our blood may have no way
因為我們血液可能沒有辦法
So fast flow to our brain
這麼快速的流到我們腦部
This makes it easy for us to fall
這樣子就很容易讓我們有跌倒的情形發生
everyone will want to say
大家會想說
Do I have to take medicine for high blood pressure?
我高血壓一定要吃藥嗎
If you say he thinks you don't need medicine
如果說一聲他覺得你不需要吃藥的話
Maybe it's just maintenance
那可能就是在平時的保養
Also, make adjustments to your usual diet
還有平時的飲食狀況來做調整
words here
那這裡的話
I have written about the comfort food
我有寫到得舒飲食
we can eat
我們可以吃
Whole-grain rhizomes So what is whole-grain rhizomes?
全穀根莖類 那請問一下大家什麼是全穀根莖類
What are whole grain rhizomes
全穀根莖類是什麼
root food
根莖類食物
radishes don't count
蘿蔔不算
Sweet potato taro?
地瓜芋頭嗎?
that vegetable
那蔬菜
Today's lunch box contains
今天中午的便當裡面有
Who has lunch from the company today?
今天中午誰有吃公司的便當
what's the dish today
今天的菜有什麼
Is this a vegetable?
對這個都算是蔬菜嗎
Everyone should know that meat
大家應該都知道那肉
what is white meat
白肉是哪些
Chicken and fish, right?
雞肉魚肉對不對
He also wrote here
他這裡也有寫到
If you want two glasses of low-fat milk a day, please ask
每天要兩杯低脂牛奶那請問一下
1 cup low-fat milk
一杯低脂牛奶
Do you know how much CC is?
大家知道是多少CC嗎
It's from the government
這是政府所推出來的
One cup is equal to 240cc, how much are two cups equal to?
一杯等於240cc那兩杯等於多少
480 is fine
480很好
It is written here that try to eat nuts and use good oil
這裡有寫到盡量吃堅果用好油
Excuse me
請問一下
nuts
堅果
daily intake
一天攝取量
should be a few grams
應該是幾公克
let me take a look
我來看一下
third in the row
最旁邊那排第三個
Brother, how many nuts do you think you eat in a day?
大哥你覺得一天攝取的堅果量
A few grams would be better
是要幾公克會比較好
One of ours is about 10 grams
我們的一把差不多是10公克
If we eat more than that, it is also accumulated in our body fat.
如果說吃超過的話那也是堆積在我們身體的脂肪裡面
come and see
來我們來看一下
This is our daily health care. Are you exercising?
這個是我們的日常保健大家平常 都有在運動嗎
Have it?
有嗎?
raised hand
有舉手
I still think that everyone
還是覺得說大家都是
We go home and work every day so tired
我們每天回家工作都好累
How is it possible that there is still time for sports activities?
怎麼可能還有時間去運動活動
me too
我也是
Ok, then I want to ask if the government has pushed
好那我想問一下之前政府有推
Do you know what the 333 movement principle is?
333運動原則大家知道什麼是333運動原則嗎
do you know
大家知道嗎
don't know good
不知道 好
333 Exercise Principles Exercise 3 days a week
333運動原則每週運動3天
Exercise 30 minutes a day
每天運動30分鐘
Then our heartbeat keeps
然後我們的心跳維持
Heart rate maintained above 130 during exercise
運動時心跳維持在130以上
This is our 333 Movement Principle
這就是我們333運動原則
Hope we can do it together
希望大家可以一起做的到
It is not recommended that the water temperature
洗澡時候水溫不建議太高或者是太低
do you know why
大家知道為什麼嗎
In fact, temperature is related to the expansion and contraction of blood vessels.
其實溫度跟血管擴張收縮都是有關係的
If your temperature is too high our blood vessels dilate
如果你的溫度太高我們的血管就會擴張
When the temperature is too low, the blood vessels constrict
溫度太低血管就會收縮
So it happens when we're cold in a state where we all shrank and shivered
所以當我們在冷的時候在我們都會縮起來寒顫的狀態發生
You can think about it
大家可以想一下
Some people with high blood pressure
有一些高血壓的人啊
He'll tell me when it's winter
他到了冬天他就會跟我說
Why is my blood pressure so high today to winter?
為什麼我今天的血壓到冬天的血壓都那麼高
That's how our blood vessels constrict when our blood is going out of our blood vessels
就是這個原理 我們的血管收縮我們的血液要從我們的血管通出去的時候
increased blood pressure
血管壓力變大
right
對不對
Our blood vessels dilate when the weather is hot in summer
我們在夏天天氣熱的時候血管擴張
In our blood vessels, the pressure of our blood flowing out will not be so great.
在我們血管我們那個血液流出去的壓力就不會這麼大
So in summer our blood pressure will not be higher than in winter
所以夏天的時候我們的血壓不會比冬天還高就是這樣
Is this clear to everyone?
這樣子講大家清楚嗎
Ok good
Ok好好
If you have high blood pressure, you will be advised to quit
血壓高的話會建議要戒菸戒酒因為抽菸真的對身體很不好
If you can quit smoking, quit smoking
如果可以戒菸的話大家要戒菸
Eat more fruits and vegetables to prevent constipation
要多吃蔬菜水果預防便秘
If you need enough sleep, please ask
睡眠的話要充足那請問一下
How many hours do we sleep a day
我們睡眠一天要睡幾個小時
six to eight hours
六到八小時
normal blood pressure
血壓的話平常啊
not written here
這裡沒寫
Eat a light diet
要以清淡飲食為主
Can you all cooperate?
大家可以配合嗎?
Light diet can not eat too salty too spicy
清淡飲食不能吃太鹹的太辣的
It should be difficult or everyone's usual diet is light
應該很難還是大家平常的飲食都是以清淡
not so salty
不會吃的那麼鹹
so good
這樣不錯
There are parts that protect your cardiovascular
有保護到你的心血管的部分
Then ask everyone
那請問一下大家
Everyone's emotions are very calm when they go to work, can they not be excited?
大家在上班的時候情緒都是很平穩的嗎可以不激動嗎
it should be hard, right?
應該很難對不對
But how can we make our emotions more stable?
但是我們要怎麼讓自己的情緒比較平穩
What do you do when you're emotional
如果說當你情緒一來的時候你要怎麼做
silent
沉默
listen to music
聽音樂
pressure relief
舒壓
I want to ask again
再來我想問一下
How to measure blood pressure
量血壓的方式
Raise your hand if you have a blood pressure monitor at home
家裡本身有血壓計的請舉手
Okay, so before you take your blood pressure
好不錯那大家在量血壓之前
Will you take a 5-10 minute break first?
會先休息的5到10分鐘嗎
would be nice
會不錯
Do you take your blood pressure immediately after
測量血壓之前大家會在運動完之後馬上量血壓嗎
Because the blood pressure will be falsely high at that time
因為那個時候血壓會假性偏高
If you want to measure blood pressure, everyone
那量血壓的話大家都會穿著比較輕便的衣服去量測
Before taking blood pressure
如果說要量血壓之前
we might be there
我們可能要在那裡
Take a 3 to 5 minute break
做個3到5分鐘休息一下
Let our whole mood be in a calm situation
讓我們的整個情緒是一個平緩的狀況下
we'll start
我們就開始
clothes like
衣服像
This eldest brother is fine, because his clothes are thinner, so
這位大哥好了因為他的衣服比較薄所以我們在量血壓的時候不需要把衣服捲上來
But if the clothes are thicker in winter
但是如果說冬天的時候衣服比較厚
We may have to take off our jackets a little bit.
我們可能衣服外套就要稍微脫一下
Then my blood pressure readings will be more accurate.
那我這樣子量測的血壓數值會比較準確一些
it is good
好
Then come again
那再來
Our feet must be flat on the ground
我們的雙腳一定要平放在地面上
Don't hang in the air or say tiptoe
不要懸空或是說墊腳尖
it is good
好
Do you know how to place the blood pressure monitor correctly?
血壓計擺放位置大家知道要怎麼擺放才是正確的嗎?
If our sphygmomanometer says you are measuring
我們血壓計如果說你在量測時候
the height of our hearts
我們心臟的高度
The height of our heart should be parallel to the sphygmomanometer
我們坐著的心臟高度要跟血壓計是平行的
because you are too high or too low
因為你太高或是太低
Blood pressure will be different
血壓量出來數值會不一樣
It is possible that the blood pressure you put this time will be lower.
有可能你這次放的比較高血壓就會比較低一點
Or if you put a lower blood pressure, the blood pressure will be higher.
或者是你放的比較低血壓就會比較高一點
It's hard to say
這些都很難說
The above words are the part I introduce about high blood pressure
以上的話是我介紹高血壓的部分
Next, I want to share the video that I just told you.
接下來我想分享一下影片就是剛剛跟大家說的
Would you be surprised if you saw this scene?
如果是你們看到這個場景會不會嚇一跳
will it? what are you going to do?
會嗎那你們要怎麼辦
CPR AED right?
CPR AED 對不對
In fact, our Taiwan government has made statistics
那其實我們台灣政府有去統計
According to statistics at the beginning of this
今年初統計出來我們心臟疾病在今年是排在
Number two in the top ten causes of death
十大死因的第二順位
In terms of myocardial infarction, it is the number one priority of heart disease.
那以心肌梗塞的話 就是心臟病的第一順位
Myocardial infarction
心肌梗塞的話你看
How harmful it is to our body
對我們身體是有多麼大的危害
Have you ever wondered what a myocardial infarction is?
大家有沒有想過什麼是心肌梗塞
Okay, let's take a look at our right image
好我們來看一下我們的右圖
The circle on the left is our normal blood vessel
左邊的那個圈圈是我們正常的血管
Normal blood vessels should not have bad things accumulated there, right?
正常的血管應該都不會有不好的東西堆積在那裡對不對
That second vein you can see he's starting to have some bad stuff
那第二個血管你可以看到他開始有一些不好的東西
It may be the accumulation of fat in the walls of our blood vessels
可能是脂肪堆積在我們血管壁
Let's see the 4th
再來看到第4張
In the fourth picture, do you see if the space for him has become smaller?
第四張你看他的那個空間是不是變小了
Then if our blood goes in from this place
那我們的血液如果從這個地方進去的話
If he goes in like this from the fourth circle, will he have greater resistance?
從第四個圈圈這樣子進去的話 他是不是阻力會比較大一些
It's possible this time
有可能這時候
He will have angina
他會有心絞痛情形發生
So if he's all blocked, it's a myocardial infarction
那如果說他全部阻塞的話這個就是心肌梗塞
Myocardial infarction within 4 minutes
心肌梗塞的話如果是在4分鐘以內
There is use to AED
有使用到AED
His survival rate will be higher
他的存活率會比較高
But if more than 4 minutes
但是如果超過4分鐘
Every minute over we increase our mortality rate by 1%
每超過1分鐘我們的死亡率就會提高1%
So at the beginning of a myocardial infarction
所以在心肌梗塞一開始的時候
I just didn't let everyone see the back
我剛剛沒有讓大家看到後面
One of the paramedics rushed right up to help him with the CPR moves.
有一位護理人員他直接衝上去幫他做CPR的動作
one thing is missing
缺少了一個東西
AED
就是AED
Why does myocardial infarction occur?
那為什麼會有心肌梗塞的發生
This yellow image is like the part of the blood vessels I was talking about
這一張黃色的圖就像我剛剛在講的血管的部分
red is our blood vessels
紅色是我們的血管
Yellow words are our fat
黃色的話是我們的脂肪
When more and more yellow places
當黃色的地方越來越多
The permeability of our blood vessels will get worse and worse
我們血管的通透性會越來越差
That's how myocardial infarction happens
那心肌梗塞就是這樣子發生
The heart has large triangular blood vessels
心臟有三角很大很大的血管
right one
右邊一條
There are two on the left
左邊有兩條
i want to ask
我想問一下
Do you know the high-risk groups for myocardial infarction?
心肌梗塞的高危險群大家知道有哪些嗎
high blood pressure
高血壓
diabetes
糖尿病
I just told you about the blood vessels
那剛剛在血管的地方有跟大家講說
Too much fat may cause his blood vessels to block
脂肪太多有可能引起他的血管阻塞
So he must also have hyperlipidemia
所以他一定也有高血脂症
postmenopausal women
更年期後的女性
In terms of high blood pressure
那以高血壓來講
he has a heart attack
他罹患心臟病
He will be bigger than us
他會比我們一般人
2.5 times more likely to suffer from heart disease
還高出2.5倍罹患心臟病
Diabetes words
糖尿病的話
Heart disease is twice as common as the average person
罹患心臟疾病的也是我們一般正常人的兩倍
Did you see the back?
大家有沒有看到後面啊
I just thought about it
就是剛剛我有唸到的
postmenopausal women
更年期後的女性
This is about our girls
這個跟我們女生有關的
because of menopause
因為更年期的時候
Our estrogen will decrease
我們的雌激素會降低
Estrogen protects our cardiovascular system
雌激素是可以保護我們的心血管
when menopause comes
當更年期到來的時候呢
How can we protect our cardiovascular system
我們要怎麼保護我們心血管
Have you ever thought about
大家有沒有想過
At this time, we can consume more beans after menopause
這時候呢我們再更年期之後可以多攝取一些豆類
Soy beans and black beans are the estrogen that women's bodies are good for
黃豆黑豆這個都是女性身體還不錯的雌激素
not bad
還不錯
So we can also add more beans when menopause comes.
所以我們也是可以之後更年期到來我就可以多補充一些豆類了
Then for the high-risk group just mentioned
那就對剛剛所說的高危險群
he is lifting heavy objects
他在提重物
after eating
吃飽之後
are prone to myocardial infarction
都很容易發生心肌梗塞的情形
I would like to ask everyone how full we have to eat each meal
我想問一下大家我們每一餐吃東西都要吃到幾分飽
seven points full
七分飽
very good
很好
and then
然後呢
Myocardial infarction is more likely to occur when the weather is very cold and hot
天氣很冷很熱的時候也很容易發生心肌梗塞的情形
Then everyone will see it on TV
再來大家一定都會在電視劇上看到
when dad wants to kill his daughter
爸爸如果要兇他的女兒的時候
At that time, there will be a myocardial
那時候就會心肌梗塞 倒在地上對不對
What do you do when you are his daughter?
這時候你是他的女兒要怎麼辦
Save him, call 119, right?
救他 打119對不對
So how do we know about our myocardial infarction?
那我們要怎麼知道我們的心肌梗塞啊
myocardial infarction it
心肌梗塞它
There must be some symptoms
一定會有一些症狀出來
This exam is very important
這個會考很重要很重要
His omen is
他的前兆就是
left shoulder pain
左肩痛到後背
shortness of breath
呼吸會有短促的情形
will sweat
會冒冷汗
Paled face
臉色蒼白
These four symptoms
這四個症狀
If you find out that someone has another myocardial infarction
如果說你發現有人心肌梗塞再發作了
I have all the symptoms I just mentioned.
就剛剛說的那些症狀都有了
Usually a doctor with heart disease will prescribe 1
那一般有心臟疾病的醫生他都會開立1個
A small piece of medicine, you can see the picture on our left
一小段的藥大家可以看到我們左邊的圖
There's a bottle of medicine on it
上面有一瓶藥
Then look at this bottle, it's really small.
那你看這一瓶要真的很小瓶
He has 25 in it
他裡面有放25顆
he is ntg
他就是ntg
He is what people call a heart-saving pill.
他就是人家講的救心丸
He is really small, so how should he eat it? The doctor will tell you then
他真的很小顆那要怎麼吃呢到時候醫生也會告訴你
That's basically when it happens
那基本上事情發生的時候
You can pick one up and put it under his tongue
你可以拿一顆起來放在他的舌下
Because we have more blood vessels under the tongue
因為我們舌下的血管會比較多
Then he will absorb better
那他吸收的狀況會比較好
But if he still doesn't get better after 5 minutes
但是如果說他在5分鐘後還是沒有緩解
Then give him a second one
那趕快再給他吃第二顆
This medicine is no more than 3 pills at most.
這個藥最多就是給3顆再多也沒有用了
At this time, you have to help him quickly call 119 and send him to the doctor.
這個時候你要幫他趕快打119去送醫了
Then if you see him, you can't take this medicine again
那如果說你看到了他沒辦法再吃這個藥
He also passed out there, no breathing, no heartbeat.
他也昏倒在那裡沒有呼吸心跳了
At this time, you have to help him do CPR as soon as possible.
這時候你要趕快幫他做CPR的動作
When we had a myocardial infarction
我們在心肌梗塞發作的時候
most important thing
最重要的事
Seek medical attention within 12 hours
12小時之內要趕快送醫
There will be two directions for the doctor to help
送醫會有兩個方向醫生去幫助
First, we will definitely do a blood draw and an electrocardiogram.
第一個我們一定會做抽血跟心電圖的檢查
Then there is the drug treatment
再來就是藥物治療
What if not
沒有的話呢
Because we may have a blood clot in the blood vessel
因為我們有可能血管內有血栓的情形發生
So the doctor will prescribe aspirin for you. Have you heard of aspirin?
所以醫生會幫你們開立阿司匹林大家有聽過阿斯匹靈嗎
He works great but the problem is
他很好用但是問題是
he has side effects
他有副作用
part of the heart
用於心臟血管的部分
He has
他有
Another is because he inhibits thrombosis
另外一個因為他是抑制血栓形成
means that our blood does not clot easily
代表我們的血液不容易凝固
What to do when we get hurt and the blood doesn't clot easily
當我們受傷然後血液不容易凝固的時候怎麼辦
Aspirin is not easy to clot blood
阿斯匹靈就是不容易讓血液凝固
then i'm hurt
那我受傷
We have no way to stop the bleeding. Usually, we can put
我們就沒辦法好好止血平常我們可能好好加壓一到兩分鐘就可以止血了
Then it may be pressurized for 5 to 10 minutes
那它可能要加壓5到10分鐘
So if you pressurize a wound for 5 to 10 minutes
那如果說你一個傷口加壓5到10分鐘
What do you do if you can't stop the bleeding for another 15 to 20 minutes?
再來15到20分鐘都沒有辦法止血的話你們要怎麼做
It's very simple, go directly to the hospital, tell the doctor
很簡單啊直接去醫院啊跟醫生講說我沒辦法止血請醫生協助我
Otherwise how long will we be there?
要不然我們要在那裡壓多久
The other is that we will have a cardiac catheterization intervention.
另外一個就是我們會有心導管的介入
Do you know what a blood vessel is?
大家知道什麼是通血管嗎
What is a blood vessel
通血管是什麼
Brother, how do you know
大哥你怎麼都知道
Let's watch the video
我們看一下影片
I just told you how many blood vessels we have in our heart
我剛剛有跟大家說了我們心臟有幾條血管
Not bad, then if I put this bracket, there will be at most a few at most
不錯喔那如果我放這個支架的話最多最多有幾條
40 records No
紀錄40幾條 沒有
It is mainly these three
主要在通的就是這三條
But he may still be blocked
可是他還有可能會有阻塞的情形
So if someone told you that he had 5 catheters
所以如果有人跟你說他在一個醫院通血管通了5條 你覺得有可能嗎?
Because the largest blood vessel has only 3
因為最大的血管只有3條
Therefore, only three blood vessels can be passed through at most.
所以通血管最多只能通三條
I want to ask everyone
我想問一下大家
If a person suddenly fell down in front of the inside today
如果說今天有一個人在裡面前突然倒下了
If someone in our company falls down in front of you
如果在我們公司有一個人在你面前倒下了
turn a blind eye
當作視而不見
Let's go and see if he's still breathing
還是過去觀望一下看他還有沒有呼吸
or call him
或是叫他一下
If it's someone you know, you should call him a little bit.
如果是自己認識的人應該會稍微去叫他一下吧
Then this is our public version of CPR and AED
那這是我們民眾版的CPR跟AED
The first call is to call the patient
第一個叫就是叫患者
But we have to make sure before we save him
但是我們一定要確定一下我們再救他之前
Is our environment safe because we can't put
我們的環境是不是安全的因為我們不可能為了救她讓自己身陷危險的地方
Just like the hanging job just now
就像剛剛那個吊掛作業
You see that there's already a hang up there. We can't go down there and help him.
你看到那個地方已經在做吊掛了 我們不可能在吊掛作業地下去幫助他
Because of this we have another risk
因為這個我們會有另外一個風險存在
If that thing falls and we're hurt, how are we going to save him?
如果那個東西掉下來連我們都會受傷那我們要怎麼救他
it is good
好
After confirming the environment, we will call
那確認環境之後我們要叫
pat him on the shoulder
拍他的雙肩
I had a lovely colleague in my first aid class
我之前上急救課程的時候有一個很可愛的同仁
He told me what to call him
他跟我說他要怎麼叫
Guess what his name is
大家猜猜他要怎麼叫
He told me he would straddle that man
他跟我說他會跨坐在那個人身上
then face him
然後臉面向他
Hands towards him and slap him
手也朝向他 然後打他巴掌
You shouldn't do that
大家應該不會這麼做吧
I was taken aback when I saw it
那時候我看到的時候我自己嚇一跳
I wonder why it's called like this
我想說怎麼會是這樣子叫
Just pat his shoulders with both hands
就是用雙手拍他的雙肩
Ask him if he is okay, Mr.
問他先生先生小姐小姐還好嗎
If he doesn't respond and doesn't breathe at all
他如果都沒有反應也沒有任何的呼吸
Now we're going to have a second call.
這時候我們就要來第二個叫了
The second call is call help
第二個叫就是call help
What if you were alone
如果是自己一個人的時候呢
Just to call 119 because you can't see anyone around
就是要打119因為你在周圍都看不到人了
We must call the second one to save him
我們一定要呼喊第二個來救他
If there are two people
如果說有兩個人
you can ask him
你可以請他
Call 119 for you
幫你打119
Then you start helping him do CPR, and the person who called 119 for you?
那你就開始幫他做CPR那幫你打119的那個人呢
You need to ask him to find AED by the way.
你要請他順便找一下AED
Everyone must be wondering how to find AEDs outside
大家一定會os在外面怎麼去找AED
Have you ever thought about
有沒有想過
In fact, I found that there are many AEDs outside,
其實我發現外面很多AED那如果你對這個環境不熟的話
There is an AED App
有一個AED的App
can go to download
可以去下載
It's called Piezoelectric
剛剛說的叫叫壓電
It's a chest press
這是壓胸
Do you know where to press the chest is correct?
壓胸的話大家知道要壓哪裡是正確的嗎
The public version is relatively simple between the nipples
民眾版的話是比較簡單兩乳頭之間
If it is the medical staff version
如果說是醫護人員版
Two horizontal fingers on the xiphoid process
劍突上二橫指
The public version is that you can directly press between the two nipples
民眾版就是兩乳頭之間就可以直接壓了
Do you know how to pose CPR gestures?
請問一下大家知道CPR的手勢要怎麼擺嗎
You can lend me both hands
大家可以雙手借我一下
A hand during our CPR
我們CPR的時候呢一隻手
it opens like this
是這樣子打開的
what about the other hand?
另外一隻手呢
meeting
會
put this
放在這個
finger gap
手指頭縫隙
Then when we are under normal pressure, we will
那我們正常在壓的時候會
Will do the pressing action with the heel part of the palm
會以這個掌跟的部分做壓的動作
Then our fingers will stick up.
那我們手指頭都是會翹起來的
Because if you hadn't jumped up, our whole point of force wouldn't be here
因為你如果手指頭沒有跳起來我們整個施力點不會在這裡
It is possible that all five fingers will exert force and spread to five fingers
有可能五隻手指頭都會有施力 分散到五隻手指頭
Our bodies are vertical when we press
我們在壓的時候身體都垂直
The heel of the palm retreats between his nipples
掌跟退到他兩乳頭中間
Press like this
這樣子按壓
Let's call it twice
我們那時候就喊一下兩下
Remember our fingers are pointing upwards
要記得我們手指頭是要向上的喔
The finger is to be upwards, so the action of pressing
手指頭是要向上的喔這樣子壓的動作
So if we say that we have been pressing down on the AED
那如果說我們一直壓壓壓到AED來
What if you say you're tired
如果說你累了話怎麼辦
Ask the next person to help you
請下一個人來幫你壓
The AED
那這個AED
Our company has two AEDs
我們公司有兩台AED
Both AEDs are the same
兩台AED都是一樣的
Our step is to open the post
我們的步驟就是 開 貼 電
Wait a minute and you'll hear it on the video
等一下大家在影片上面會聽到
The AED that is plugged in is another model
開 貼 插 電那個AED是另外一個型號的
If it is different, then our company will issue a call
比較不一樣那我們公司就開貼電
Opening the AED's box is the same as turning on our power
打開AED的盒子就是等同打開我們的電源
Do you know where to post it?
貼的話大家知道要貼哪裡嗎
If you don't know, the sticker will tell you where to put it
如果不知道的話那個貼片上面都會告訴你要貼哪裡
what we normal people want to post
我們正常人要貼的話
One is attached under our right collarbone
一個是貼在我們的右鎖骨下方
You should have felt your collarbone.
大家應該有摸到自己的鎖骨吧
Tell me if you haven't touched it
沒有摸到的跟我說
The right clavicle should be there.
右邊鎖骨應該都有吧
If the other piece, we will stick it on the side of the left nipple
另外一片的話我們會貼在左側乳頭側邊
When the patch on our AED is turned on, the patch will tell you where to put it
我們AED那個貼片打開的話那個貼片就會告訴你要貼在哪裡
don't worry
大家都不要擔心
For the children, because their body size is relatively small
那小朋友的話因為他們身體面積比較小
So he is the part before and after the post
所以他是貼前後的部分
If the electricity is used, everyone knows that it is to shock him.
電的話呢大家就知道了就是要電擊他
What if before the shock
如果在電擊之前呢
to tell everyone
要跟大家說
Please leave or everyone will be called by you together
請大家離開要不然大家都會一起被你電到
Because people are also conductive
因為人也是導電的
Then let's watch the video
那我們來看一下影片
I want to ask everyone
我想請問一下大家
This topic is also important
這個題目也很重要
Excuse me, where is our company's AED?
請問一下我們公司AED擺在哪裡啊
can you tell me
大家可以告訴我嗎
What about the restaurant?
餐廳還有呢?
where else
還有哪裡
see pictures and tell stories
看圖說故事
Did you see
大家有看到嗎
except the restaurant
除了餐廳
There are also two places in the health center that have AEDs.
還有健康中心這兩個地方有AED喔
This is the item inside our AED
這是我們AED裡面的物品
stickers included
包含了貼片
And the battery
還有電池
Do you think this first aid kit is strange?
大家看一下這個急救包有沒有覺得很奇怪
why he needs scissors
為什麼他需要剪刀
Why does Aed need scissors
Aed為什麼要剪刀
cut clothes pair
剪開衣服對
Then why the razor
那為什麼要剃刀
why
為什麼
Do some guys have thick chest hair?
有些男生的胸毛很茂密嗎
Because I'm afraid you'll get hairy
因為怕你弄到毛
Then his conductive effect will also deviate
然後他的導電效果也會偏差
So if say
所以如果說
If you cut his clothes and found a lot of hair on his chest
你幫他剪開衣服發現到他胸毛很多的話
Don't be rude, just shave him
就不要客氣了就直接幫他刮毛
because to save him
因為為了救他
So what I want to share with you is this
那這一張的話想要跟大家分享的就是
If today you find that the fallen person is covered with water or around him
如果說今天你發現倒下的人他的身上或者是附近都是水
please move it to a dry place
請你把它移到乾燥的地方
Also wipe the water off him
也要把他身上的水擦乾淨
Because everyone should also know that water conducts electricity, right?
因為大家應該也會知道水會導電吧
I just said
剛剛我說的
Do not touch the patient during the shock
在電擊的時候不要去摸病人
Water is also a conductive material, so please
水的話因為也是導電的物質所以請大家
Wipe the water off him and move it to a dry place before you can do the electric shock.
把他身上的水擦乾移到乾燥的地方才可以做電擊的動作
If you have high blood pressure, you just stopped for about
高血壓的話剛剛差不多1個小時停下來有沒有覺得高血壓很可怕
Affects many, many organs of the body
影響很多很多身體的器官
So everyone, take good care of your body
所以大家身體要好好保重
That's it for today's class, thank you all
我今天的課講到這裡 謝謝大家